Guide to the Robert Benton Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Robert Benton Papers
1969-1994
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Benton, Robert
SWWC.096
24 Linear Feet
45 boxes Plus items in map case, framed art case, and oversized.
The Robert Benton Papers document the filmmaking career of the Oscar- winning writer and director. Works represented include Kramer vs. Kramer, Still of the Night, Nadine, Places in the Heart, Billy Bathgate, and Nobody's Fool. Materials include scripts, notes, production and publicity materials, photographs, and set designs for films Benton wrote and/or directed.
Scope and Contents
The Robert Benton Papers document the filmmaking career of the Oscar-winning writer and director from 1969-1994. The collection is arranged in six series: personal papers (1940s, 1987 and 1984); produced works (1972-1994); unproduced works (1969-1988); works by others (including works from Walter Bernstein and Naomi Foner); photographs; artwork (storyboards, posters, and set designs); and framed photoprints.
The bulk of the collection represents some of Benton's most seminal works including screenplays, notes, publicity, and other production material from his produced films, Bad Company, Kramer vs. Kramer, Still of the Night, Nadine, Places in the Heart, Billy Bathgate, and Nobody's Fool.
The papers also include the screenplays, scripts, and notes from some of Benton's unproduced works including "Hubba-Hubba or Will the Big Bands Ever Come Back?," "The Coast," "Stardust," "Magic Hour," and the manuscript for Benton's unpublished novel, "Lover – A Novel of Suspense." Photographs, contact sheets, publicity stills, and color slides from Benton's produced films provide visual documentation of the filmmaking process, as do numerous story boards from Nadine and Places in the Heart, movie posters from nine of Benton's projects, set designs from Billy Bathgate, and framed photoprints of Benton on set with actors such as Dustin Hoffman and Bruce Willis.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert Benton, 2001
Biographical Note
Writer and director Robert Douglass Benton was born on September 29, 1932, in Waxahachie, Texas. He is the son of Ellery Douglass and Dorothy (Spaulding) Benton. Benton attended The University of Texas at Austin and received a BFA in 1953. His classmates included Jayne Mansfield and Rip Torn, an actor he would direct in the 1987 film Nadine. While serving in the U.S. Army from 1954-1956, Benton painted dioramas at Fort Bliss. He was discharged with the rank of corporal. He enrolled at Columbia University to study Art History but dropped out after one semester. Benton would then begin his professional career as a freelance writer and artistic associate at Esquire.
Benton remained with Esquire for several years where he worked in various editorial capacities. Here he would meet future collaborator David Newman. The pair published Extremism: A Non-Book (1959) and wrote the libretto for the Broadway musical It's a Bird…It's a Plane…It's Superman (1966). Benton's first film industry success was with Bonnie and Clyde (1967), a screenplay he co-wrote with Newman. Starring Faye Dunaway and Warren Beatty, the film was critically acclaimed and Benton and Newman received an Oscar nomination for best story and screenplay. His other early writing credits include There Was a Crooked Man (1970), What's Up Doc (1972), and Oh! Calcutta! (1972).
Paramount president Stanley Jaffe encouraged Benton to move into directing. He made his directorial debut in 1972 with Bad Company, a wild west adaptation of Dickens' Oliver Twist starring Jeff Bridges, Barry Brown, and David Huddleston. Benton directed The Late Show in 1977 and wrote the screenplay for Superman (with Mario Puzo and David and Leslie Newman) in 1978. His next directorial role was with the 1979 film Kramer vs. Kramer. A box office hit and critical success, the film won the Oscar for Best Picture while Dustin Hoffman and Meryl Streep also won Oscars for their performances. Benton won Oscars for Best Director and Best Screenplay.
1982's Still of the Night saw Benton direct Meryl Streep again in a starring role. Benton directed and wrote the screenplay for Places in the Heart (1984), a semi-autobiographical film starring Sally Field. The film was honored with two Oscars; Benton won Best Screenplay while Field won Best Actress. He wrote and directed Nadine in 1987 and directed Billy Bathgate, an adaptation of an E.L. Doctorow novel, in 1991. It was the first film that Benton directed but did not write. Benton directed Paul Newman in the 1994 adaptation of Richard Russo's Nobody's Fool. A friendship was forged and Benton and Newman worked together again on Twilight (1998). Benton directed the 2003 adaptation of Phillip Roth's The Human Stain. His most recent work as a director is the 2007 film Feast of Love. Benton is currently working on the screenplay for North of Cheyenne, slated for a 2011 release.
Index Terms
Subjects
Feature films; Screenwriters -- United States
- Personal Papers, 1940s, 1984, 1987; 3219
  Scope and Contents
  The smallest of the series, it consists of papers regarding Italy (1940s), information on a computer, clippings from the Bakker scandal (1987), and a playbill from Death of a Salesman.
  - Papers regarding Italy, 1940s (2 folders), 3225 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Subject file – Computer, 3227 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Subject file – Jim, Tammy, Jessica (clippings of Bakker scandal), 1987; 3228 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Playbill, Death of a Salesman, April 1984; 3229 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Produced Work, 1972-1994; 3220
  Produced works comprise the bulk of the collection. It consists of screenplays, notes, publicity, and other production material for the films Bad Company, Kramer vs. Kramer, Still of the Night, Nadine, Places in the Heart, Billy Bathgate, and Nobody's Fool.
  - Bad Company, 1972; 3230
    - Screenplay "release dialogue script", October 2, 1972; 3256 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Kramer vs. Kramer, 1977, undated; 3231
    - Scripts, 1977, undated
      - First draft, October 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Revised first draft, working copy with Tom Marks' cut, October 27, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Second draft, working copy, October 27, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - First draft pages, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - First draft revision pages, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Screenplay, pages 21-147, heavily annotated, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Screenplay, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Screenplay draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Notes, 3238
      - Screenplay with Renata's script notes and packing inventory, July 1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Publicity, 1979-1980; 3239
      - Publicity clippings, 1979-1980; 3266 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Still of the Night (Working title "Stab"), 1976-1982, undated; 3232
    - Scripts, 1976-1981
      - Notes on characters Sam and Brooke (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Outlines, annotated (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
      - "Stab" screenplay, revised, January 7, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - "Stab" screenplay, revised, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Screenplay, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Screenplay, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Screenplay master (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Draft screenplay (out of order) (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - First draft screenplay (3 folders), January 1976 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
      - irst draft screenplay, January 1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Second draft screenplay, undated (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
      - "Stab" second draft typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - "Stab" third draft screenplay (2 folders), July 1980 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
      - Third draft screenplay, unrevised, July 24, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Master third draft, July 1980 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Revised screenplay, January 16, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Screenplay, Benton work copy, January 19, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Revised screenplay, February 6, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Revised screenplay, master copy, February 6, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Revised screenplay, February 27, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Production Materials, 1982
      - Continuity notes, June 1982 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Post production material (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Publicity
      - English language reviews (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
      - Foreign press reviews (Box 7, Folder 2-4)
    - Notes, undated
      - Script with outline notes (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Script pages (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Looping notes (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Script notes (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Screenplay pages (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Nadine, 1985-1986; 3233
    - Scripts, 1985-1986
      - First draft, October 1985 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Screenplay, November 1985 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - First draft, February 1986 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Screenplay, Wolfgang numbered copy, April 3, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - First draft (W.G.), April 29, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Draft, April 29, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Draft, May 15, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Annotated draft, May 15, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Draft, July 9, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - First draft (2 folders)s), August 12, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 6-7)
      - First draft, revised, August 25, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - First draft, revised, August 25, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - First draft fragment, April 29, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Partial draft, March 15, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Screenplay, fragment, April 22, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - First draft, second revision, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Production Materials, 1986; 3245
      - Production Schedule (3 folders), 1986; 3322 (Box 10, Folder 6-8)
  - Places in the Heart (Originally "Texas Picture"), 1982, undated; 3234
    - Scripts, 1982-1983
      - Treatment, "Praise, Blame, Love...", September 1982 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Treatment, "Praise, Blame, Love...", October 1982 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Working copy, "Praise, Blame, Love..." (2 folders), November 24, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
      - Working copy, "Praise, Blame, Love...", December 20, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Working copy, "Praise, Blame, Love...", undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - First draft, January 20, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - First draft, January 24, 1982 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - First draft (2 folders), January 31, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 4-5)
      - Second draft, March 1983 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - Second draft, revised (2 folders), March 1983 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
      - Second draft, notes and revisions, March 1983 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Second draft, revisions and miscellaneous pages, March 1983 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Second draft, revised, East Texas, May 1983 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Second draft, revised (3 folders), July 25, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
      - Second draft (2 folders), undated (Box 14, Folder 4-5)
      - Second draft, first 88 pages, undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - Second draft, annotated, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Production Materials
      - Extra continuity (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Main title sequence, miscellaneous brothers material (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - Opening title sequence (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Production notes (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - Production schedule (3 folders) (Box 15, Folder 6-8)
      - Production schedule, continued (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Sound cue list (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Publicity
      - Studio publicity pack (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Broadcast excerpts (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Foreign publicity (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - Foreign publicity, continued (2 folders) (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
      - Newspaper clippings (6 folders) (Box 17, Folder 3-8)
      - Newspaper clippings, continued (4 folders) (Box 18, Folder 1-4)
      - Periodicals (2 folders), Screening lists and information (Box 18, Folder 5-7)
    - Awards
      - Academy Awards publicity (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Notes
      - Bootleg information (Box 19, Folder 2)
      - Casting notes (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - Script fragments (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - Script fragments and yellow pages (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - Yellow pages (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Billy Bathgate, 1990, undated; 3235
    - Scripts, 1990, undated
      - Screenplay, March 1990 (Box 19, Folder 7)
      - First draft, revised (2 folders), March 1990 (Box 19, Folder 8-9)
      - First draft, revised (3 folders), March 1990 (Box 20, Folder 1-3)
      - Second draft, May 1990 (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - Second draft, revised (4 folders), May 25, 1990 (Box 20, Folder 5-8)
      - Third draft (4 folders), une 15, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 1-4)
      - Screenplay, Doctorow's notes, pages 54-113, July 20, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 5)
      - Screenplay, Doctorow's notes (2 folders), July 20, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 6-7)
      - Screenplay, Doctorow's notes, pages 1-55, 54-113 (2 folders), July 20, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 8-9)
      - Third draft, revised (2 folders), August 6, 1990 (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
      - Third draft, revised, editorial equipment rentals, August 6, 1990 (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - Third draft, revised, August 6, 1990 (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - Third draft, second revision, August 6, 1990 (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - Third draft, second revision (2 folders), September 6, 1990 (Box 22, Folder 6-7)
      - Third draft, second revision, September 6, 1990 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Fourth draft, annotated notes, September 12, 1990 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - Fourth draft, September 12, 1990 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - Fourth draft, revised (2 folders), September 14, 1990 (Box 23, Folder 4-5)
      - Fourth draft, September 14, 1990. Revisions: first blue (September 20, 1990), second pink (September 25, 1990) (Box 23, Folder 6-8)
      - Annotated draft, pages 1-57, undated (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - Annotated draft with handwritten notes, pages 1-53 (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - Annotated draft, pages 102-137, 15-58 (Box 24, Folder 3)
      - Screenplay, pages 108-164 from Doctorow, undated (Box 24, Folder 4)
      - Screenplay (5 folders), undated (Box 24, Folder 5-9)
      - Screenplay, annotated, labeled "Anne Rapp", undated (Box 24, Folder 10)
      - Draft fragment, undated (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - Production Materials, 1991, undated
      - Screenplay, various portions and notes, undated (2 folders) (Box 25, Folder 1-2)
      - Production schedule (December-January) (2 folders) (Box 25, Folder 3-4)
      - Production schedule; Revised Screenplay (2 folders), September 1991 (Box 25, Folder 5-6)
  - Nobody's Fool, 1993-1994; 3236
    - Scripts, 1993
      - Clean screenplay, March 15, 1993 (Box 26, Folder 1)
      - Annotated script, June 24, 1993 (Box 26, Folder 2)
      - Clean screenplay (2 folders), August 13, 1993 (Box 26, Folder 3-4)
      - Clean screenplay, September 15, 1993 (Box 26, Folder 5)
      - Clean Part II, pages 253-414 (Box 26, Folder 6)
      - Clean Volume III, pages 502-707 (Box 26, Folder 7)
      - Clean Volume IV, pages 708-937 (Box 27, Folder 1)
      - Annotated Part I, pages 1-252 (Box 27, Folder 2)
      - Annotated Part II, pages 253-501 (Box 27, Folder 3)
      - Annotated Part III, pages 502-707 (Box 27, Folder 4)
      - Annotated Part IV, pages 708-937 (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - Annotated Part II, pages 253-501 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Notes
      - Outlines and notes (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Production Materials
      - Extra pages (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - Combined continuity and spotting list, October 12, 1994 (Box 28, Folder 5)
- Unproduced Works, 1969-1989; 3221
  This series consists of scripts/screenplays and notes from projects that have not been produced, and a manuscript for the unpublished novel "Lover – A Novel of Suspense." The unproduced works are "Hubba-Hubba or Will the Big Bands Ever Come Back?," "The Coast," "Stardust," and "Magic Hour."
  - Hubba-Hubba or Will the Big Bands Ever Come Back?, 1969; 3450
    - Screenplay, annotated, September 2, 1969; 3455 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Screenplay, clean, undated; 3456 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - The Coast, 1975; 3451
    - Screenplay, first draft, April 1975; 3457 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Stardust, 1988, undated; 3452
    - Script, first draft, March 8, 1988; 3458 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Screenplay, draft, March 28, 1988; 3459 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Screenplay, draft with notes, April 4, 1988; 3460 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Screenplay, first draft, undated; 3461 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Notes and outline, undated; 3462 (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - Magic Hour, undated; 3453
    - Screenplay, first draft (2 folders), undated; 3463 (Box 30, Folder 1-2)
  - Lover - A Novel of Suspense, undated; 3454
    - Manuscript, annotated by Benton, undated; 3465 (Box 30, Folder 3)
- Works by Others, 1986-1990; 3222
  The works by others in this series are from Sullivan Street (by Walter Bernstein), Hoffa (by David Mamet), and The Homesman or Seeing the Elephant (by Naomi Foner).
  - Sullivan Street (by Watler Bernstein), 1986; 3466
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Scripts, 1986, undated
      - Drafts (7 versions), January 22 through February 25, 1986 (Box 30, Folder 5-10)
      - Drafts (9 versions), February 25 through June 9, 1986 (Box 31, Folder 1-9)
      - Script and loose pages (2 folders), undated (Box 32, Folder 1-2)
    - Notes: "Peter's file", undated (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Hoffa, 1990; 3467
    - Screenplay, June 1990; 3492 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - The Homesman or Seeing the Elephant (by Naomi Foner), 1990; 3468
    - Screenplay, second draft, November 1990; 3493 (Box 32, Folder 5)
- Photographs, 1981-1996; 3223
  This series is the second largest and includes photographs from Still of the Night, Places in the Heart, Billy Bathgate, Nobody's Fool, and Magic Hour.
  - Still of the Night, 3494
    - Contact Sheets (2 folders), 3499 (Box 33, Folder 1-2)
    - Publicity Stills, 3500 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Photographs, 3501
      - Meryl Streep (Box 33, Folder 4)
      - Roy Scheider (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Meryl Streep and Roy Scheider (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - Group photos and other cast (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - Production photos (Box 34, Folder 4)
      - Various 4 x 5 photographs (Box 34, Folder 5)
      - Various 4 x 5 photographs (2 folders) (Box 35, Folder 1-2)
      - Negatives (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Places in the Heart (originally Texas Project), 3495
    - Contact sheets of Danny Glover, 3521 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Contact sheets of photographs by Zade Rosenthal (3 folders), 3522 (Box 35, Folder 5-7)
    - Color slides, 3526 (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - Photographs
      - Sally Field (alone) (Box 35, Folder 9)
      - Danny Glover (alone) (Box 35, Folder 10)
      - John Malkovich (alone) (Box 36, Folder 1)
      - Individual shots of other cast members (Box 36, Folder 2)
      - Groups shots of cast members (Box 36, Folder 3)
      - Sally Field and children (not part of production) (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Snapshots (5 boxes), 3505 (Box 37, Box 38, Box 39, Box 40, Box 41)
  - Billy Bathgate, 3496
    - 11x14 color photograph from set, 3538 (Map-case Dr. 9)
  - Nobody's Fool, 3497
    - Contact sheets NF5000-NF5149 (missing NF5018 – NF5037) (4 folders), 3539 (Box 42, Folder 1-4)
    - Contact sheets NF5150-NF5215 (2 folders), 3543 (Box 43, Folder 1-2)
  - Magic Hour, 3498
    - Contact sheets (3 folders), 3546 (Box 43, Folder 3-5)
    - Contact sheets (2 folders), 3549 (Box 44, Folder 1-2)
    - Publicity stills, 3551 (Box 44, Folder 3)
- Artwork/Oversized Materials, 3224
  This series consists of story boards, posters, set designs, set drawings, set plans, and framed photoprints that are oversized and do not fit into standard size archival boxes. It includes story boards from Nadine and Places in the Heart; posters from Still of the Night, Billy Bathgate, Bad Company, The Late Show, Places in the Heart, Kramer vs. Kramer, Nobody's Fool, Nadine (French version), and Twilight; set designs/drawings from Billy Bathgate; framed two photographs of Benton with Dustin Hoffman and Bruce Willis, and Benton with Bruce Willis; and Johnson's New Map of Texas.
  - Story Boards, 3552
    - Nadine, Frame 42, #23-29, and 3 unnumbered storyboards, 3557 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Places in the Heart, Frame 41, 4 unnumbered storyboards, 3558 (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - Posters, 3553
    - Still of the Night, Billy Bathgate, Places in the Heart, Nadine (French version), Twilight, 3559 (Map-case Dr. 9)
    - Bad Company, The Late Show, Kramer vs. Kramer, Nobody's Fool, 3561 (Frame Upper A Bin 16)
  - Set Designs/Set Drawings/Set Plans, 3554
    - Billy Bathgate set designs, set drawings, and set plans, 3555 (Map-case Dr. 9)
  - Framed Photo Prints, 3556
    - Benton on set with Dustin Hoffman and Bruce Willis; Benton on set with Bruce Willis; Johnson's New Map of Texas, 3562 (Frame Upper A Bin 16)